距离地球4亿英里 存在这一个迷你太阳系
Four hundred million miles from Earth, exists a mini solar system
60多个卫星围绕着一个强大的气态行星旋转
of over 60 moons rotating around a powerful planet of gas.
它流动的颜色和斑点保持了奇异的美景
Its flowing colors and spots hold strange beauty,
然而也包含了强烈的风暴 喷射气流
but contain violent storms and jet streams.
这个巨大明亮的大气球会是伯利恒之星吗？
Could this big, bright ball of weather have been the Star of Bethlehem?
它的其中的一个卫星会有生命生存在冰盖下吗？
Could one of its moons harbor life beneath its icy crust?
我们认为生命分枝会存在在木卫二上
We expect that branches of life would exist on Europa,
只是因为水是其主要特征
just simply because water is the key feature.
我想去木卫二冰下垂钓
I wanna go ice-fishing on Europa.
打个洞潜入水中 看看四周  看到如果有什么…
Cut a hole, put a submersible, look around, see if anything…
有什么朝照相机游过来 拍打照相机
if anything swims up to the camera and licks the camera.
这就是我想做的
That's what I wanna do.
我们地球要感激这个庞大的滑稽的磁体吗？
And does our own planet owe its survival to this massive comic magnet?
木星--巨大的行星
Jupiter, the giant planet.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
历史频道·宇宙第一季第4集 木星·巨大的行星
影片压制:暮云春树  字幕来源：射手网 调校：TIAN@CMCT 招募Q号: 76846146
木星距离太阳5亿英里
Jupiter is half a billion miles from the Sun.
一个巨大的结构复杂的星球
A giant sphere of intrigue.
这个旋转着的气态星球看上去象一幅艺术家的画作
This turning ball of gas may look like an artist's rendering,
然而却是真实的物体
but it's the real thing.
木星具有太阳系里最奇特的气象模式
Jupiter has the most exotic weather patterns we had ever seen in the solar system.
木星有84%的氢
Jupiter is 84% hydrogen
差不多14%的氦
and almost 14% helium,
这两个是宇宙里最轻和最多的元素
the two lightest and most abundant elements in the Universe,
组成它庞大的身躯
rolled into a mammoth mass.
这家伙的直径是地球的11倍
This thing is eleven times the diameter of Earth,
你可以轻松地将1000个地球塞进木星里
and you could take a thousand Earths and stuffed them inside Jupiter comfortably.
木星真的是太阳系里的霸主
Jupiter really is the lord of the solar system.
知道吗 行星的大约70%左右的物质在木星里
You know, about 70% of the mass in all the planets is in Jupiter.
如果你谈论行星 木星是团伙里最大的孩子
If you talking about planets, Jupiter is the big boy in the block and
它真的称雄称霸
it really does rule the roost.
木星是太阳系里最大的行星
Jupiter is the largest planet in the solar system.
肉眼能明显地看到
Visible to the naked eye.
木星上一天只有9.9小时长
A day is only 9.9 hours long.
围绕太阳转一圈需要11.86年
And it takes 11.86 years to orbit the Sun.
150磅重的人在木星上会重达350磅
A 150 pound person would weight 350 pounds on Jupiter.
有氨 硫磺和水组成的雷雨云
There are thunder clouds made of ammonia, sulfur and water.
探索木星是美国宇航局迄今最大胆的使命
Exploring Jupiter would be NASA's most daring mission to date.
这是一个不友善的地方 温度极端
It's a hostile place, with temperature extremes,
从冰箱到火炉
from fridging to firing.
它的电磁辐射很强
Its electromagnetic radiation is intense.
会顷刻杀死来访者
It could kill a traveler to the planet in an instant.
我们需要厚重的铅的保护
We would need heavy lead protection
使得在地面上举步艰难
and that's very difficult to lift off the ground.
实际上人们到木星去
So we have some difficult engineering challenges
在工程上是个艰难的挑战
to actually bring human beings to the planet Jupiter.
在木星登陆是..不会发生的
A landing on Jupiter is… not going to happen.
木星本身是个非常气态的行星
Jupiter itself is a very gassy planet.
是由气体组成的 所以你…
It's made of gas. So you…
不会有固体的地表站立和四处走动
would not have a solid surface on which to land and walk around.
只会不断下降穿过云层然后最终坠毁
You would just keep descending through the clouds and then be eventually crashed
靠着木星大气层的压力
by the pressure of Jupiter's atmosphere.
那就使得人们到木星旅行具有挑战
That make a human trip to Jupiter quite a challenge.
如果我们能去那里
But what if we could go there.
安德鲁·英格索尔博士行星的权威
Doctor Andrew Ingersoll is an authority on the planet.
他带我们做一次环游
He takes us for a ride.
你需要一个特别的气球
You need a special kind of balloon,
因为木星的大气层是氢气
because the Jupiter's atmosphere is hydrogen.
氢是最轻的气体
Hydrogen is the lightest gas.
载人气球会下沉
A human balloon would sink.
所以唯一的情况是在寒冷的氢大气层里
So the only thing that'll flow in a cold hydrogen atmosphere
用热的氢气漂流
is hot hydrogen.
因此需要加热气球里的氢气
And so you need a hot-air hydrogen balloon.
在过去的10年里 美国宇航局研发着
For the past ten years, NASA has been developing
超长期限的气球 用于机械人探测
ultra-long duration balloons, for robotic exploration.
正如我们知道的那样  加热氢气是件棘手的事情
And as we all know, heating hydrogen is a tricky thing.
但究竟这个巨头是如何诞生的仍然是个谜
But just how this behemoth was born, is a puzzle.
木星的形成关联着行星最大的谜团
The formation of Jupiter is the greatest mystery associated with the planet.
有人认为木星可能是不合格的恒星
Some believe Jupiter may have been a failed star.
就象太阳一样有着合适的成分
Like the Sun, it had the right ingredients,
氢和氦
hydrogen and helium.
但是没有足够的质量形成内部核融化
But not enough mass to create the internal pressure and temperature
所需要的压力和温度
necessary to have nuclear fusion.
所以它变成了行星
So, it became a planet instead.
理论上那里有银河系的星云
The theory is that there was this cloud in the galaxy
和太阳的成分一样的
that had the same composition of the Sun.
在它自己的引力下塌缩
And it collapsed under its own gravity and some stuff
有些东西还是留了下来
was left behind.
留下的部分成为了行星
And that stuff became the planets.
多数变成了木星
And the majority of that stuff became Jupiter.
其余的当然跑进了太阳
And the rest, of course, went into the Sun.
有几个细小的残留物 就象地球
And there were a couple of little tiny leftovers, like Earth.
木星旋转的气体吸引了轻的元素
Jupiter's spinning gasses attracted light elements,
在这过程中成长得越来越大
and overtime grew bigger and bigger in the process.
几乎就象牡蛎 围绕着沙粒一层一层制作着珍珠
Almost like an oyster, creating layers around the grain of sand to make a pearl.
没有被木星摄取的气体和固体
What gasses and solids Jupiter didn't ingest,
被加速抛入太空
it sped out into space.
所以木星就象在校园里的大哥哥
So Jupiter is like the big brother in the schoolyard,
保护着你免受威胁你生存的浩劫的欺凌
protecting you from bullies that might wreak havoc on your existence.
我倾向于认为它更象宇宙飞盘家伙
I tend to think of it as more of the cosmic Frisbee guy.
它把物体抛出太空
It's grabbing things out of space
也把物体折腾回来
and it's also tossing them back out.
它处死来自太阳系内部的物体
It ends up keeping those objects from the inner solar system,
那里有地球 火星和金星
where Earth and Mars and Venus are.
通过清理一些碎片
By cleaning some of the debris up,
把一些抛出去 把一些射到太阳里去
kicking some of it out, shooting some of it into the Sun,
这样碎片就会永远消失
where it would be lost forever,
木星清理出一条道路让其它行星
Jupiter cleaned out a path that the other planets could
保持一些安静
exist in some sort of peace.
飞盘现象的如此优势
So dominant is this Frisbee phenomenon,
地球可以将生存归功于木星
Earth may owe its very existence to Jupiter.
它影响到慧星 甚至一些流星和小行星的路线
It influences the courses of comets and even some meteors and asteroids,
因此通过施加在近地物体上的作用
so that over the NEOs the effect of Jupiter is there,
帮助照顾太阳系附近的物体
helps takes care what comes near the solar system.
这么看来木星的存在真的是地球产生生命的原因之一
So really the presence of Jupiter may be one reason why we have life on Earth
通过打击大量的慧星 使地球成为可居住之地
and habitability and be able to have the Earth nice environment
有着美好环境
instead of getting pummeled by so many comets.
没有比木星在1994年七月的七天里
There is no greater proof of Jupiter's power play
爆发的力量更有力的证据了
than what happened during the seven day period in July of 1994.
一颗名叫苏梅克列维9号的彗星
A comet called Shoemaker-Levy 9
向着木星高速行进
barreled toward Jupiter.
就在木星的影响下一去不复返
Once under Jupiter's influence there was no going back.
物体和气体星球发生了碰撞
A missile was on a crash course with a ball of gas.
木星的引力是如此的巨大
Jupiter's gravitational pull was so great
把慧星拉成碎片
that it broke the comet into small pieces
一次一个
that came in one at a time.
这些碎片以每秒37英里的速度攻击木星
These pieces assaulted the planet at a speed of 37 miles per second.
当物体以超音速行进时
When you have a missile going at supersonic speeds
会感到震动
you get a shock.
可以看到物体产生的云从地面上腾起
You can see sort of clouds of material being jetted up from beneath where it landed.
一个火球在与木星大气层的碰撞中升起
One of the fire balls generated by the collision with Jupiter's atmosphere
高达1800英里
flared 1,800 miles in the space.
至少可以这么说 在地球的范围内
Had Earth been in the projectile sights
这种打击将是灾难性的
the effects of such a smash up would have been catastrophic to say the least.
类似的打击已经灭绝了恐龙
Similar to the event that wiped out the dinosaurs.
那些碎片打击释放的能量
The energies that were released in those fragments hitting
不管怎样要十倍或二十倍于
was larger than anywhere of ten or twenty times
全球所有武器的能量总和
more powerful than the entire world arsenal of bombs.
把木星拿走
Take Jupiter out of the picture,
把这颗慧星放到太阳系里
bring this giant comet into the inner solar system,
它会到哪里去？
where would it have gone?
我们不知道
We have no idea.
可能会撞击地球
Might have crashed into Earth.
如果那颗慧星撞进地球  这里周围的一切将会完全不一样
If that comet had crashed into Earth, things would be a lot different around here.
专家们认为打击木星的慧星
The experts believe that comet strikes on Jupiter
可能比那些撞击地球的物体大8000倍
may be 8,000 times more frequent that those on Earth
大大感谢飞盘的作用
thanks to the Frisbee effect.
两败俱伤 因为木星没有价值系统
But it cut both ways because Jupiter has no value system,
当它看到一个犯错的慧星就可能吸引并吞噬它
when it sees an erring comet it may attract it and swallow it up.
但是投掷的地方可以是任意的
But where it flings is anyone's guess
所以犯错误的慧星可以被投向地球
and so erring comets can be flung in towards Earth,
也可以投进太阳
they can be flung into the Sun,
也可以投出太阳系
they can be flung out of the solar system.
前提是行星拒绝一些太空垃圾挡住自己的道
There's a reason the planet rejects some of the space junk heading its way.
木星是太阳系里最大的行星 有着最大的引力
Jupiter being the biggest object in the solar system has the most gravity.
因此其它物体会逐个逃离
And so other objects literally flees,
它们有自己的行进轨道
they have their own trajectory flying by, are bent
在那里它们通常会以加速度奔向木星
from where it would be towards Jupiter and usually with an acceleration.
而加速度有时会将它正好被撵出来
And that acceleration can cause it sometimes to just be ejected completely.
地球上没有飞盘投掷者能和木星投掷力相媲美
No earthly Frisbee thrower can match Jupiter's flinging force.
我们知道这比子弹要快的多
It is much faster than any bullet ever known.
其反作用力的速度达每秒30英里
It rejects things at a rate of 30 miles per second.
木星奇观的是难以探测的
Jupiter's wonders are hard to fathom.
迷惑人类已经几个世纪了
They've captivated men for centuries.
史前人们认识到它在恒星之间运动
Prehistoric humans realized that it was moving among the stars
是他们欣赏的行星之一
and it was one of the planets that they appreciated.
木星是上帝之王
Jupiter was the king of the Gods,
毕竟在罗马神话里是这样
after all, in Roman mythology.
而且圣经也曾提到过木星
And there may be a biblical reference to Jupiter.
打从五岁开始 我记得人们说过:
Ever since I was like five years old I remember people:
"噢 那是颗伯利恒之星 "
"Oh, that was the star of Bethlehem!"
不论是否真的 我们无法知道
And whether or not it really was, obviously we have no way of knowing,
然而还不清楚关于那颗星
but it's not clear whether the star that was talked about
是单一的星体还是一个天体的天文联盟
is a single star or whether they met an astronomical alignment
我们没有真正了解
of objects in the sky, we don't really know.
按照科学述语它是联合体
It's known as conjunction in scientific terms.
按照对木星和金星的研究
According to researches Jupiter and Venus
公元前3年8月作为大的类星体发布
did appear as one large star-like object in August 3 B.C.,
会在东方的夜空看到
and would had been visible in eastern night sky.
然而现代天文学之父伽利略
But it was Galileo, the father of modern astronomy,
首次记载了看到的木星系统
who made the first recorded sighting of the Jupiter system.
在1610年早期 望远镜发明后仅仅18个月
In the early days of 1610, only about 18 months after the telescope was invented,
他用自己的望远镜看到了木星
he got his own telescope and he was on Jupiter.
在1665年木星最迷人的面貌被揭开
In 1665 Jupiter's most fascinating feature was discovered.
它那巨大的红眼实际上是巨大的风暴之眼
Its giant "red eye" was actually the eye of an enormous storm.
完全不同于地球上的东西
Unlike any experienced on Earth.
这在300年前引起一场狂热
This one has raged for at least 300 hundred years.
这个天象搅乱了气象学家的梦
This weather disturbance is a meteorologist's dream.
木星巨大的红斑实在是大
Jupiter's Great Red Spot, is truly huge.
你可以把地球展开放进去  甚至还无法盖住这个红斑
You can take Earth and flare it out and then wouldn't even really cover the Spot.
这个风暴是太阳系里最大的
This storm is the hugest storm in the solar system.
感觉大约宽12000英里
And just to give a feeling about it, it's about 12,000 miles.
地球却只有8000英里宽
And the Earth is only 8,000 miles wide.
风围绕其边缘快速流动
And the winds blow quiet fast around the edge.
然而其中心很平静
But it's calm in the center.
它…它不象飓风那样
It's… It's not like a hurricane
有一个眼并且中心有狂风
which has an eye and very fast turbulent winds in the center.
红斑相当平静
Red Spot is rather calm.
如果你有个气球 可以很舒适的飞行
If you're in a balloon, it might be a pleasant ride.
只要你能避开小规模的地方
As long as you avoided the small scale stuff
诸如雷暴和吵闹的地方
like the thunderstorms and the turbulent places.
即使你跑的很快 它也相当平静
Even though you'd be going very fast it might be quite calm.
可以快达每小时350英里
Fast as in 350 miles an hour.
地球上曾经记录到每小时175英里的风速
The fastest wind ever recorded here on Earth was 175 miles an hour.
但那是象地球上一样的风暴吗？
But is it an Earth-like storm?
它吸纳了周围紊乱的云
It's a giant collection of clouds roiling around,
雷电轰鸣…
lightning going on…
因此我们只能模拟它的情景
So we can only model an imagine of what kind of precipitation
各种气体凝结成蒸汽存在
but condensation in the form of condensed vapor of various gasses.
这个著名的红斑是个高压系统
This famous Red Spot is a high pressure system
能够在10天里完全翻转
that can take 10 days to complete a rotation.
确实向后的飓风称为反气旋
Truly a backwards hurricane is called an anticyclone,
那是对那些旋转方向向后的典型飓风的命名
that's the name for those circles backwards on the direction of a typical hurricane.
它不仅仅是好奇的东西
That's not the only curious thing.
正如我们知道的飓风 需要水才能形成
Hurricanes, as we know them, need water in order to form.
然而红斑里没有水的动力
There's no water engine in the Red Spot.
这个永不停顿的天气系统有点象别的东西
This never-ending weather system is feeding on something else.
是什么？
But what?
木星大红斑象不停的飓风
Jupiter's Great Red Spot is something like a non-stop hurricane.
它是庞大的风暴 全部是狂风和雷电
It's a colossal storm, complete with violent wind and lightning.
风暴猎人喜欢跟着它跑
Storm chasers would love to go running after it.
路易斯维耳大学的蒂姆·道林博士
Dr. Tim Dowling of the University of Louisville
热衷于地球上相似的现象
is in the hot for similar phenomena here on Earth.
红斑是… 认为它象是个庞大的极端…
The Red Spot is…  Think of it as a huge extreme…
***陆地或***巨大的鸡蛋形状 一个巨大的
***lands or*** egg shape of mass, such as an enormous thing that sort of
平静下来的气流 把它压进温度较高的内部
quiets down the fluid and the presses it down into the hotter interior
所以不会有雷击
so you don't get thunderstrokes.
但是如果进入到红斑的边缘 特别是在西北部
But if you go on the edge of the Red Spot, specially north-west,
就会看到木星上最可怕的雷暴
you get some of the most horrific thunderstorms you're gonna find on Jupiter.
红斑没有一个眼 它不是用水来驱动的
The Spot doesn't have an eye and it isn't fueled by water.
自从它形成以来就没有海洋
There's no ocean over which it forms.
那么是什么使它保持周而复始的运行的呢？
What then keeps it going and going?
我总是把它比作我看到的…象
I've always liken it in my own view as… like a mini volcano
木星里的一座迷你火山
inside of Jupiter.
实际上是座大气火山
Actually an atmospheric volcano.
贝恩斯博士认为是木星里的热加热了气体上升
Dr. Baines believes that warmer gasses rise from heat, deep within the planet.
气体试图逃逸时产生了旋涡
While trying to escape they create a vortex.
所以基于这些理由 我相信那里正好有额外的能量
So, for some reason I believe there's extra energy right there.
但这不是理论
But it's just a theory.
科学对这个问题以及其它一直没有答案
Science is left without answers to that question and others.
当前理论上还无法解释红斑为什么如此完美
Current theories cannot quite explain why the Spot is so well-formed
为什么会存在一颗行星上
and why it stays in one place.
科学家多年研究的积累更多
The plot thickened over the years as scientists learnt even more.
它变得更扑朔迷离
It became a deeper mystery because
是因为围绕着红斑平静运行的一切
instead of everything just sort of smooth going around the Red Spot,
我们看上去是混乱的
we saw there's turbulence and
有小的物体每天在来回
there were smaller scale structures that come and go every day,
是混乱无序的 然而红斑控制着它们的生存
and it was chaotic and triggering and yet the Red Spot just existed and stayed hold on.
木星风暴不仅仅限定在大红斑里
Jupiter's storms aren't limited to the Great Red Spot.
云厚厚地遮盖三层 遮盖着行星
Cloud decks three layers thick hover and cover the planet.
如果你在木星的大气层里 你会听到
If you were inside the atmosphere of Jupiter you would hear
非常响的雷鸣 事实上雷声传播
very loud thunders. In fact we have thunders
的速度居然比地球上快4倍
actually which travel four times faster on Jupiter than it does on Earth.
每小时大约3000英里
It's about 3,000 miles an hour.
落下的雨是地球上的两倍快
So rain falls twice as fast on Jupiter.
正电荷被推向云层的顶部
The charge separation that pulls the positive charges to the top of the clouds
负电荷被推向云层底部 这在木星上
and the negative charges to the bottom of the clouds is twice as efficient
是独一无二的快两倍 这是因为下的鱼要快两倍的缘故
on Jupiter for that reason alone, because the rain is falling so much faster.
在木星上看到的塔状积雨云比地球的高三倍
Towers of cumulous convection that you see on Jupiter are three times taller.
高达30英里 而地球上的只有6-7英里高
They go up 30 miles whereas on Earth they go up 6 or 7 miles.
它在大红斑里不可能存在
It would be impossible to survive within the Great Red Spot,
因为那有每小时350英里的风
with its 350 mile-an-hour winds.
作为比较 飓风威尔玛
By comparison, hurricane Wilma,
目前世界上有记录的最高风速
which had the highest recorded winds of any earthly storm,
2005年严创尤卡坦半岛
slammed into the Yucatan peninsula in 2005 with barely a breath,
风速达到每小时175英里
175 mile-an-hour blasts.
地球的天气是简单的 木星的天气是复杂的
Our weather is simple, Jupiter's is complex.
在木星上基本上
Now on Jupiter you just basically have
是一个风暴接着一个风暴 一个接着一个
one storm system sort of stacked on another stacked on another
伴随着许许多多的摩擦
with lots and lots of rub.
基本上那些风暴是其自然状态
Basically these are the storms in their natural state.
这些风暴在木星上无情地移动
These storms move relentlessly within Jupiter's other distinct feature,
凶猛的气流围绕木星不断流动
streams of fierce jets that continually circle the planet.
科学家还只是开始了解
Scientists are only beginning to understand
风暴是什么和从哪里来
what they are and where they come from.
这有朝东的流动的物质
There is a massive eastward flow of material
意味着…
and that means…
物质以每秒一个半足球场的速度流动
the material's flowing more than one and a half football fields per second.
那真的是在流动 你不会想呆在那的
That's really moving, you don't want to be in that.
改变着宽度方向的29地带和其它地区 从那往外扩展
29 other belts and zones of varying width extend outwards from there.
给了木星特有的面貌
They are what give Jupiter its characteristic appearance.
它们交叉移动 有时向东 有时向西
They move in alternating directions, some eastward, some westward.
高纬度的要比近赤道的规模要小得多
They're much smaller scale the high latitude jets than the equatorial one,
对照一下地球上的距离
as far as in comparison to Earth these are massive,
超高速 高速的风刚好反过来
super-fast high-speed winds and yet they're just going back and forth.
这和行星自转的速度有关
The planet's rotation rate has something to do with it.
木星产生大量的能量是因为它确实的运转
Jupiter generates a lot of energy because it really moves.
所以非常自然的旋转使得
So the very nature of the spinning causes
木星不仅仅产生一个风暴 还会产生更多的风暴
Jupiter to not just have one jet stream but many jet streams
围绕着行星的相对应的方向
going in opposite directions along the planet.
所以你会看到这些地方 所以
And so you can see these zones, so what you have
会有地球基本气象模式的夸张写照
is an exaggerated version of Earth's basic weather pattern.
表面云产生壮观的气旋会分区碰头
The spectacular swirls are created in surface clouds where the zones meet.
这被认为是能量最后带动这一带
It's believed that the energy ultimately powering this belt phenomenon
剧烈的热从深处出来的现象
comes from intense heat deep within.
不同于我们每天所看到的现象
It's not unlike something we see every day.
买一个水壶装上水放在炉子上
Buy a boiler pot of water on a stove, it'll start bubbling
它会开始从壶底往上冒泡 努力挣脱
and bubbles come out from the bottom and try to get out trying to
里面的水流不断循环 所以…
circulate that water that currents around, so…
同样的事情也发生在木星内 气体和液体
same thing inside Jupiter, we have gases and liquids down there
下降下去 热释放出来
that are trying to get the heat out.
有个基本问题 基本的物理原理去
There are basic questions, basic pieces of physics to go after
解释大规模的气流
to explain the massive jets.
我们能够解释这个问题？
Shouldn't we be able to explain that?
地球就有一个主要的气流往东移动
Earth has just one primary jet stream, it moves eastward,
而另外一个主要的气流往西移动 所谓的信风
and another major flow that blows westward, the trade winds.
木星上的气流的能量是地球的三倍
Triple that power and you've got the jet streams of Jupiter.
一切都不同于地球 而且…
Totally different from Earth. And yet…
我要说清楚 并不是与地球完全不一样  只是地球有点超常
I should be careful, not totally different from Earth, just Earth on steroids.
你问你自己 哇
And you ask yourself, wow!
如果你不了解木星上在发生什么
If I understood what's going on on Jupiter,
地球就会是个样板
Earth would be  just a piece of cake.
木星的奥秘并不局限于它本身
Jupiter's mysteries aren't limited to the planet itself.
它最迷人的东西围绕着它运行
Some of its most intriguing elements are circling around it.
木星有几十个卫星 大的可以看到
Jupiter's got several dozen moons that are big enough to be seen
大概还有许许多多太小了  现代技术还无法看到
and has probably got a lot more that are too small to be seen with current technology
毫无疑问 将来会发现它们
and no doubt in coming years more will be discovered.
一些卫星几乎有着行星般的大小
Some of the moons almost have the size of some planets.
所以木星真的有着自己的太阳系
So really Jupiter has its own little solar system.
多谢它那难以置信的引力
Thanks to its incredible gravitational pull,
把小行星连同其它太空碎片拉住
it sucked in asteroids along with other space debris.
其中大部分是有序的
For the most part there is order.
然而有一些轨道飘忽不定的卫星
But there are some erratic moons in orbit around Jupiter.
它得对付混乱
It's managed chaos.
你能想象出一连串奔跑者
Can you imagine a bunch of runners
沿着跑道 各自停下而不相撞
in the track, in their lanes, each runner stays and they won't collide.
这是一种天上的技巧
It's kind of a celestial mechanics.
每个卫星把握这自己的魔力
Each moon holds its own fascination.
四个突出的木星卫星是伽利略发现的
Four of Jupiter's prominent moons were discovered by Galileo.
他首次看到它们围绕着木星运转
He first observed that they revolved around the planet.
它们根据木星都被以上帝的情人来命名
They are named for Jupiter, the god's lovers.
你第一个来到的主要的卫星是爱莪(木卫一)
The first major moon you come into is Io,
是个非常活跃的地方 有着大量的火山
which is this very active place. There are lots of volcanoes.
几乎随时都在喷发
It's almost all the time going off.
喷出200英里的岩浆进入太空
Shooting out magma 200 miles into space,
木卫一100多座火山是个奇迹
Io is a wonder pop-mark with over a hundred volcanoes,
一些加利福尼亚大小的火山似乎时开时关
some the size of California which seem to turn themselves on and off.
伽尼墨德(木卫三)是太阳系里最大的卫星
Ganymede is the largest moon in our solar system.
有地球卫星月亮五倍这么大  卡莉斯托(木卫四)有着最沉重的撞击
Five times the size of Earth's Moon. Callisto is the most heavily cratered.
在它的生命周期里 明显地遭受了打击
It has clearly taken a beating in its lifetime.
接着是欧罗巴(木卫二) 木星国王的冰王后
Then there is Europa, the ice queen to Jupiter's king.
没人确切地了解其构造
No one knows its make-up for sure.
它看上去象个破碎的鸡蛋
It looks like a cracked egg.
它真的好象上面整个环绕着水
It really looks like the whole thing had looped
有时结冰 有时破裂
water on it sometime it froze and it cracked.
我们认为那种现象是潮汐的力量在破碎
And we believe that these patterns are due to tidal forces that crack it.
木卫二与众不同的是似乎一些地方是平滑的  其它地方是丘陵
As alien as Europa seems it is smooth and glassy in some spots, hilly in others.
事实上它与地球上的一个冰冻世界相似
In fact it is remarkably similar to one of Earth's frozen wonderlands.
南极有个湖叫做东方号
There is a lake in Antarctica called lake Vostok that scientists think is
科学家认为与木卫二看到的相似
an analogy to what we see on Europa.
南极有着厚重的冰盖 下面是液态的湖
Antarctica has a huge thick ice crust and underneath there is this liquid lake.
我们认为与木卫二上看到的可能非常相似
And we think this may be very similar to the water ice underneath the surface
冰盖下有水
that we see on Europa.
如果你到外壳下面可能得到冰 甚至水
If you go down through the crust you got to the ice and then if you get
我们非常相信下面会有液态水
liquid water. And we are very convinced that there's liquid water down there.
它是我们已知的地球以外存在水
It's the only place that we know, beside the Earth
和大量水的附着体的唯一的地方
which has liquid water and large bodies that have been there, we believe
我们认为已经存在了一百万或两百万年了
for more than a million or two million years.
那 有水的地方会有生命吗？
And where there's water, could there be life?
木星的卫星木卫二充满了秘密
Jupiter's moon Europa is bursting with secrets.
甚至可能在其冰壳的下面深处隐藏着温暖的热喷口
It may even have warm thermal vents deep below its frozen crust.
事实上 那有个比太平洋更大的广阔的海洋
In fact there's an immense ocean that's bigger than the Pacific Ocean
有一半的水在那里
worth half liquid water down there.
那里孕育着情况的发生
That is sitting there for things to happen to.
水的存在意味着一件事
The presence of water means one thing.
我们可能并不孤独
We may not be alone.
我想去木卫二冰下钓鱼
I wanna go ice-fishing on Europa.
打个洞潜到水里 瞧瞧四周看有没有东西…
Cut a hole, put a submersible, look around, see if anything…
有什么游到照相机前 轻轻拍打相机
anything swims up to the camera and licks the camera.
这是我想做的
That's what I wanna do.
一位科学家就在做这样的垂钓旅行计划
One scientist is planning just such a fishing trip.
在这个得克萨斯州奥斯汀附近的室外实验室里  希望系于一个小机器人身上
At this outdoor lab, near Austin, Texas, hopes are hanging on a little robot.
它被设计用于未知的地方探险
This is designed for exploration
完全未知的地方
in unknown territory, completely unknown territory,
搜索生命
and search for biological live.
它是深井热量探测器 简称"DepthX"
It's a DEep Phreatic THermal eXplorer, or "DepthX" for short.
它现在所处的场所是当地的一个采石场
Its proving ground right now is a local quarry.
对它的将来有个很大的计划
And there are big plans for its future.
如果一切按照计划执行  我们将在2017年进行发射
If everything went according the plan we would launch around 2017.
将会在2018年抵达木卫二…
It would be at Europa by 2018…
在2019年的某个时候  我们将会知道地球外是否存在生命
and by 2019 for certain we'll know whether there's life off Earth.
这是个赌博
That's the game.
深井热量探测器是工程师比尔·斯通的创作
DepthX is the brainchild of engineer Bill Stone.
他和一组科学家已经将他们的声誉和它绑在了一起
He and a team of scientists have staked their reputations on it.
他们化了6年时间来做研发和建立模型
They spent 6 years developing the concept and building the prototype.
是雄心勃勃计划的一部分  将看着它被带进太空
It's part of an ambitious project that would see it carried into space,
通过6英里的冰进到木卫二的海洋里
sent through 6 miles of ice and into Europa's ocean.
它被分离下降成为不一样的航天器
To divide it down into all the various vehicle, you have a
母船在绕木卫二的轨道上运行
a parent vehicle which takes you to orbit around the moon Europa.
可能有个登陆车…
There would be a lander…
会登陆在冰上的陆地上
that would land on the ice,
接着登陆车进入第二阶段
then there's a second stage of the lander which melts its way
融化3到5公里厚的冰盖 此时进入第三阶段
from 3 to 5 kilometers of ice cap and then at that point you kick out the 3rd stage.
我们需要一个快速移动的装置 就象鱼雷一样
We need a fast moving device, that would be sort of torpedo-shaped,
很有可能是核动力的
most likely nuclear propelled.
它将围绕木卫二中央海洋行进几千公里
And that would drive for thousands of kilometers around the central ocean of Europa.
这真的可行吗？美国航天局认为可行
Is that really feasible? NASA thinks so.
这个航天器装载着金钱和祝福
The space agency is onboard with the money and its blessing,
一项搜索生命的投资
an investment in the search for life.
如果生命存在于木星的卫星木卫二上  那么它们会走路 说话或飞翔吗？
If life exists on Jupiter's moon Europa, could it walk, talk or fly?
会不会是小细菌 会是最好的细菌？
It would be little viruses or no, maybe a best bacteria?
我们只能期待看到原始的生命形式
We would expect only to see primitive life forms.
但可能是我们在地球上看到过的  我们只是不知道而已
But they might be some more else that we see on Earth, we just don't know.
在地球最不适合居住的地方发现
Scientists are encouraged by the discovering of strange and hardy lifeforms
陌生勇敢的生命形式鼓舞着科学家
found in the most inhospitable places on Earth.
例如 两种蠕虫
Two worms, for example,
在完全黑暗的地方生存繁衍
survive and thrive in total darkness.
极端的压力不成问题
Extreme pressure isn't a problem.
这些生物在1977年被发现
The creatures were discovered in 1977
在加拉帕戈斯裂谷以下几英里的地方发现
several miles below the surface of the Galapagos rift.
它们生存在水里 高温喷口的附近
They exist in water, near superheated thermal vents.
相信这些极端条件
It's believed that these very conditions,
黑暗 高压和高温
darkness, high pressure and hydrothermal vents,
就存在在木卫二上
are present on Europa.
如果在木卫二地核下和附近
If you could have hydrothermal vents
能够发现喷口
kicking out warmth and nutrients
喷出热和养分
down and near the core of Europa,
就能哺育生物
and organisms would have fed off of that material
就象早期的地球
just likely might have in the early Earth.
虽然两个蠕虫不可能隐藏在木卫二的冰盖下
And while two worms might not be lurking beneath Europa's icy shell,
但至少会有东西的
something else could be.
这种微生物是地球上的大量的生命
This microbial life is the bulk of life on Earth.
我们期待这些生命的分枝会存在于木卫二上
We expect that branches of that type of life would exists on Europa,
只是因为水是其中的关键
just simply because water is the key feature.
寻找生命折磨着科学家比尔·斯通
Finding it consumes scientist Bill Stone.
深井热量探测器可能是揭开知识奥秘的答案
Its DepthX may answer a question that excites secrets of knowledge.
我们有机器人寻找
And we have the robot behavior look for
生命的痕迹
signs of life
接着搜集找到的样本
and then try to collect the samples based of what it's sensing.
斯通的婴儿还处于幼年
Stone's baby is in its infancy.
同时它也是超前的 高级的
At the same time it is futuristic and advanced.
它是高科技的玩具 不象其它
It's a high tech toy like no other,
可以显示我们世界另外的东西
that might show our world what another is all about.
我们第一次接触地外生命
Our first contact with extraterrestrial life
可能在木星的卫星木卫二上
may be on Jupiter's moon, Europa.
深井热量探测器更准确地叫法"水下机器人"
The DepthX robot, or more accurately "Hydrobot",
设计成会自己思考 行动和探索
is being designed to ultimately think, move and explore
而不需要人的帮助
without help from man.
全靠机器人自己做到
And that is all to be done by the robot itself.
我们将不会遥控它
We're not gonna be guiding it to do that.
这是一个将要做的大的步骤  我们会称之为机器人科学自治
That's gonna be a big step forward in what we would call robot science autonomy.
这是个人间地狱
It's a real life hell.
一个新的太空奥德赛的开始
The start of a new "Space Odyssey".
我们在底部
We're literally
边缘逐个
at the bottom edge
分类察看 会重复察看
let the type look surface and we won't see it again
直到告诉了我们下面有什么
until it tell us what's down there.
深潜水热探险者在海洋里航行时
DepthX would be able to extract and analyze samples
能够自己提取分析样本
on its own as it navigates the ocean.
我们看到的下部伸出的管子会采集水样
This outer tube we see down here  is where we pull in water samples
并储存在后面的袋子里  车上装有五个这样的东西
and store them in one later bag,  we have five of them on-board.
然而早做之前
But before it does that
实际上通过左边的微型泵连续工作
it actually powers through a series of micro pumps here on the left
把水带到随车的显微镜下
and brings it into and on-board microscope.
显微镜将摄取图象
And that microscope will take images
可以看到水里5微米左右的物体
of what's in the water down to about five microns.
所以我们几乎能够看到典型的微生物
So we can see most of the typical types of microbial life,
在屏幕上看到从5微米到200微米的
from five to two hundred microns, on screen.
如果有生命的话 机器人用这来分别测定
The robot will use that to discriminate to determine if there is life
接着提取样本
and then grab a sample.
深潜水热探险者及其系统必须做得较小便于太空活动
DepthX and its systems must be made smaller to work in space
而且还必须通过浮冰的考验
and it still must pass trials under ice floes.
我们在南极测试它
We are testing this in Antarctica
完全能在冰下可靠工作
to make sure all works totally under ice.
木卫二上的生命可能是未知的大餐
The question of life on Europa is probably the big meal***unknown,
主要是它可能会改变我们对宇宙的认识
because that would change our view of the Universe, basically.
我是指 如果这个小卫星在那里
I mean, if this little moon sitting out there
在木星恶劣的环境下
in his hostile environment of Jupiter
能够有生命存在
can have life form on it,
那就意味着或许会告诉我们
that means that probably tell us that,
生命几乎到处存在
that life is almost everywhere.
存在痕迹 我是说 认为搜索生命是一件
The sign is there, I mean, I think searching for like is one of the most
最引人瞩目的事情 我们能够做的..
compelling things that we can do as…
不仅仅是科学家做的 而且还是种族…就象人类做的
as not only as scientist but as a race… as human beings.
这是一个巨大的引导 不仅仅是对人类
It's a giant lead, and not just for mankind.
也不是对机器人族
Nor for robot kind.
在所有木星壮丽的映像里
Of all Jupiter's imposing features,
没有一个比你无法看到的更让人映像深刻
none is more impressive than the one you cannot see.
它远比大红斑大
It's bigger by far than the Great Red Spot,
比气流喷射更具活力
more dynamic than the bands of jet streams,
可以媲美人们了解的任何杀手
and as lethal as any killer known to men.
这是一个太阳系里最强烈的辐射环境
You have one of the most powerful radiation environment
还包括太阳
in the solar system, beside from the Sun.
我认为木星的磁场是太阳系里最大的
The magnetic field of Jupiter is the largest entity, I believe, in the solar system.
它是个4.5亿英里长泡沫
It is a bubble, 450 million miles long
充满电荷粒子
buzzing with electrically charged particles.
这是木星的磁气圈
It's Jupiter's magnetosphere.
太阳把太阳风送到这里
The Sun's sitting here putting out the solar wind,
太阳风充满了质子和电子
and the solar wind is charged particle of protons and electrons.
这些粒子流以每小时1英里的速度前进
These particles flow along at 1 million miles an hour.
木星基本上捕捉到了这些质子和电子
And Jupiter basically capture these sort of protons and electrons.
所有这些粒子是电流
All these charged particles are electrical current
并且环绕着木星流动
and is has it then in the space circling around Jupiter
英语中没有一个词汇能够准确地表达这种环境的恶劣
No word in the english language accurately conveys the enormity of this phenomenon.
木星的磁气圈是太阳系里最大的
The magnetosphere of Jupiter is the biggest object is the solar system.
要比太阳大得多
Is a lot bigger than the Sun.
对它最好的比喻
Comparisons are the best measure
是魔力无边的奇迹
of this mega-mighty-wonder.
如果在夜空显现
If it were visible in the night sky,
会比月亮大许多许多倍
it would be many, many times bigger than the moon.
它是个巨大的东西
It's enormous. Even though
尽管它距离地球是太阳距离地球的五倍
it's five times as far away from Earth as the Sun is,
我们仍然可以在夜晚看到它
it still would look immense in the night sky.
如果看到的话 它会以惯常的面孔出现:风向袋
If visible it would take a familiar form: a windsock.
有一个完美的面孔以一个方向对着地球
There's a rounded section facing away from the planet, in one direction,
拖着长长的尾巴
with a tail flowing out the other.
这个风向袋的延伸到土星的轨道
This windsock reaches the outer orbit of Saturn.
木星产生着1000万安培的电流
Power plant Jupiter generates up to ten million amps of electrical current.
这个太阳系里最大的行星
The biggest planet in the solar system
可以操控所有经过它周围的电流
can conduct electricity all the way through and around it.
这产生了我们能够看到的一种现象
This conductivity creates a phenomenon we can see,
此时激发了带电粒子逃逸
when the excited charged particles escape.
木星有极光
Jupiter has auroras,
因为在这些粒子进入大气层的时候会发光
because when those particles leak in and crash into the upper atmosphere, it glows.
就象地球的极光
Just as Earth has auroras.
这些可怕的极光要1000倍地
These ghostly auroras are a thousand times more powerful
强于地球南极和北极的极光
than Earth's northern and southern lights.
它们处在1200英里高空
They measure up to 1,200 miles across.
在它们下面看的话 它们弥漫着整个天空
If you could stand under them, they'd fill the entire sky,
以每小时一万英里闪电般的速度移动
moving at lightning speed, ten thousand miles an hour.
木星的磁场是个嚎叫着的怪物
Jupiter's magnetic field is a monster and it roars.
事实上是在对我们演讲 就在现在
In fact it's speaking to us, right now.
木星…
Jupiter…
太阳系里的巨人在向我们说着什么  如果你注意听的话
The giant of the solar system has something to say, if you're listening.
我们能够听到的称为"狮吼"
We can hear what we call "lion roars",
是因为它是咆哮的声音
'cause it has this roaring sound.
我们能够听到吹口哨的声音 听到嘘声…
We can hear whistler modes, we can hear hiss…
口哨是这样形成的:
And whistles that are going:
这些是动力学的原理
And these are all indications of dynamics
物体在磁气圈里产生的
things that are happening in the magnetosphere now.
如果你发现自己在昏暗的沙漠高速公路上行驶
If you find yourself driving on a dark desert highway,
车上的无线电刚好调到木星磁气圈发出的声音
your AM radio might just tune in to the strange sounds of Jupiter's magnetosphere.
脉冲短则几秒 长则几分钟
The bursts are as short as a few seconds, and as long as a couple of minutes.
每时每刻变化不断
They come and go every hour too.
大部分声音就象静电  但是每次都是在你拿起东西的时候
Most of it sounds like static, but every once in a while you pick up something
声音就象拿起或放下石头
that sounds like a rising tone or a falling tone.
听众形容无线电的声音象啄木鸟
Sound listeners have described audio spasms that sound like woodpeckers
或者象海浪冲刷着海滩 噪音真的很烦
or waves crashing on the beach. The noise is disturbing.
然而这就是行星的演讲 保持的一个谜
But just why the planet was talking, remained a mystery until Voyager II
直到1979年航海者2号经过磁气圈的外层后
passed through the outer magnetosphere, in 1979.
长期以来 没人真正明白那些信号是如何产生的
Nobody really understood for a long time how those signals were generated.
所以那是我对木星感兴趣时
So that was one of those things that
关注的一个情况
was on my mind when I got interested in Jupiter. What in the world was going on
这些无线电喷发究竟是什么？
with these radio emissions?
这是木星最终要被解开的一个迷团
It is one of the few secrets finally surrendered by Jupiter.
虽然解答了一些问题 但新的问题又凸现出来
And that answered some questions but it raised new ones.
这个…我想这是个途径 如果你没有问题
And… I think that's the way it should be. If you don't have questions,
会是讨厌的忍耐 所以…
it gets kind of boring endures. So…
我想事实上行星不可能轻易地被揭开秘密
I think that the fact that the planets don't give up their secrets easily,
或者宇宙不可能 这是游戏的一部分  这就是让人感兴趣的地方
or the Universe doesn't, that's part of the game, it's what it makes it interesting.
木星继续迷惑着科学家
Jupiter keeps astounding and confounding scientists.
一个惊奇来自1979年 当时发现木星有个环
One surprise came in 1979, when it was discovered that Jupiter has a ring.
这对土星没什么 但却是另外一个迷人的地方
It's nothing on the order of Saturn's, still, it's another feature that fascinates.
所有的大行星都有环
All of the giant planets have rings,
或许是来自行星形成时的残余物
probably leftover from when the planets formed,
卫星在气体外凝结
and the moons coagulated out of the gas that was there and then
而这可能是没有成功的卫星
it could be a failed moon.
所以木星的环来自一个内部的卫星的碎片
So, Jupiter's ring comes from material being knocked off
所以它收集了来自来自外面的卫星的尘埃
of one of the interior moons. So its dust is collected from material that's coming in from outside moons.
随着新的物质进入 环慢慢地长大
The ring is slowly growing as new material flows into it.
并且这个行星的另一面还是一个谜
And there's a whole other side of the planet that remains a mystery.
为什么这个风暴斑能够保持
Why do the storm spots keep forming.
例如 有一个暗斑
There's the Dark Spot, for example.
在1997年被首次看到
Glimpses of it were first spied in 1997.
它是地球两倍大的巨大云团
It appeared to be a huge ominous cloud twice the size of Earth,
盘旋在木星败绩上空
hovering above Jupiter's North Pole.
还有许多其它的斑点
There's a host of other spots too.
有其它小的来来往往
There are other sort of smaller cousins that have come and gone,
有红斑三分之二大小的三个卵状物
there were three ovals about half a third of the size of the Red Spot.
它们占据着相同的纬度 结束在大气层的南方
And they used to occupy the same latitude end in the southern atmosphere.
它们自1930年以来就一直在运行
And they've been around since the 1930's.
以及…业余天文家说发现至少在90年代还在运行
And… amateur astronomers saw them formed and they were around till the late 90's
而且其中的两个已经合并 接着还有两个也合并了
and they… two of them merged with each other, and then the remaining two merged,
现在只有一个了
and now there's one.
它继续在变形
And it keeps transforming.
它们在6个月前围绕着红斑运行
They have turned to red about six months ago,
现在它被称为小红斑
and it's now call it the Little Red Spot,
因为它会改变颜色 而为什么会改变颜色是个谜
because it turned color and why did they turn color is a big question.
化学或某种矢量动力学在继续
So there's chemistry going on, or some type of vector dynamics
我们需要开始研究
is going out it just kicked in and we need to start studying that.
木星是不怀好意的 不安宁的行星
Jupiter is a hostile and restless planet.
它那气态身躯和强烈的风暴
Its giant gaseous body and violent storms,
产生了太阳系里最不一样的环境
make it one of the most alien environments in the solar system.
即使它距离我们有5亿英里
Even though it is half a billion miles from us,
还是与我们要比我们想象的有更多的共同点
we may have more in common with our cousin planet than we think.
我认为从木星学习的是…
I think the lesson to learn from Jupiter here is…
无论我们的气候和气象模式怎样变化
Whatever's going on in our climate and our weather patterns here on Earth,
木星要厉害的多 但是地球不是个安全岛
Jupiter has more of it, but Earth is not an island,
地球上发生的最好的例子甚至要比地球本身来得好
and they're better examples of what 's going on on Earth than even Earth itself.
木星是关于我们太阳系许多问题的关键
For scientists, Jupiter is the king of many questions concerning our solar system,
科学家可能会掌握它的答案
and could possibly hold the answers.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing